♪Wind♪
♪바람이 설레는 정담을 살포시 놓고 가요♪
♪Whispers of love♪
♪정담은 한 사람만 꺾을 수 있기에 아름답죠♪
♪The prosperous life♪
♪번화는 우리가 함께 보낸 사계절이에요♪
♪For the rest of my life♪
♪여생은 달빛을 보며 사랑을 속삭이고 싶어요♪
♪I'll remain elegant for you all my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 아름답고 싶어요♪
♪Giving you my love little by little♪
♪조금씩 사랑을 내려놓고♪
♪I care for you with every piece of my heart♪
♪한결같이 걱정하며♪
♪And I miss you every day and night♪
♪평생 그리워하죠♪
♪I'll be loyal to you in the best years of my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 노력할게요♪
♪Melting love with gentle smiles♪
♪웃음으로 사랑을 녹여요♪
♪I won't be afraid of anything♪
♪비바람이 불어도 두렵지 않아요♪
♪And I won't change my heart for you♪
♪해마다 거두는 찻잎처럼 말이죠♪
=Episode 8=
=제8화=
Assassins.
살수다
Assassins!
사람 살려
Your Highness, what happened?
왕야, 무슨 일입니까?
- Your Highness.
왕야, 왕야
- I'm not dead. - Are you all right, Your Highness?
본왕은 죽지 않았어
I'm not dead.
아직 살아 있어
What happened?
왜 그러십니까?
Your Highness, you had a nightmare again?
왕야 또 악몽을 꾸신 거예요?
Yang Xu, Yang Xu.
양욱
At the Lantern Festival,
그날 꽃등절에서
someone assassinated me.
누가 날 죽이려 했어
Then I was killed.
내가 죽었다고
Umm...
아니...
Your Highness, I was by your side that day.
왕야, 그날 제가 계속 곁에 있었잖아요?
Look, you're exactly alive.
지금 이리
I was dead.
본왕은 죽었어
- How come...? - Dead.
어찌...
Your Highness.
왕야
Are you bewitched or something, Your Highness?
왕야, 귀신이 들린 거예요?
Come on. Stop crying.
그만들 울어
His Highness isn't dead.
왕야 살아 계시잖아
Come on, Your Highness.
왕야
Don't scare yourself.
스스로 겁주지 마세요
Am I really all right?
정말로 멀쩡한 거야?
Look at your strong body.
이 단단한 몸을 보세요
It's pretty good.
건강하시잖아요
But...
하나
I still think I was killed.
죽은 듯한 기분이 드는데
Your Highness,
왕야
what do we do?
이를 어떡합니까
It's your fault.
다 당신 탓이에요
You led to all this.
당신 때문에 우리 왕야가 이리됐잖아요
It's all your fault.
책임져요
Don't cry, Your Highness. Come on.
왕야, 그만 우세요
Your Highness, hang in there.
왕야, 꼭 버티셔야 합니다
This robe is indeed evil.
이 옷에 귀신이 깃들었소
Pick it up.
들어보시오
Master, I was wearing this robe
대사 내가 그날 이 옷을 입은 채
when I was shot to death.
화살에 맞아 죽었다네
Master,
대사님
is His Highness really bewitched?
왕야께서 정말 귀신이 들린 건가요?
This robe is actually in good condition.
아무리 봐도 옷은 멀쩡하잖아요
Oh, I see.
그런 거였군
Give me my sword.
검을 가져와
Master, save me.
대사, 날 살려주게
Your Highness, don't say anything now.
왕야 잠시만 입을 다물어 주십시오
Your Highness, the evilness is gone.
왕야, 귀신을 제거했으니
You can rest assured.
이제 안심하세요
Really?
참말인가?
Yes.
그럼요
- Your Highness.
왕야, 왕야
I do feel...
본왕은
- Better? - Indeed.
- 나으셨나요? - 이제 괜찮구나
I feel much better.
훨씬 편해졌어
- Is that true? - Really?
정말요?
Master, you helped me get rid of the evilness.
귀신을 쫓아냈으니
I shall greatly reward you.
상을 톡톡히 주겠네
- Dongxue. - Here.
동설
Take him to the counting house for the reward.
- 대사께 상을 내려라 - 예
- Yes. - Thank you, Your Highness.
황공합니다
Master,
사부님
did we really get rid of the evilness?
정말 제거했어요?
I just calmed him down.
그냥 마음의 위로일 뿐이야
There's no such thing as evilness.
괴상한 미신은 입에 담지 않는 법이다
I'm such a survivor.
본왕은 역시 팔자가 좋아
- The evilness haunted me. - That's right.
귀신이 들어도 대사님이 도와주셨고
I even survived the assassination in the South Street.
암살도 쉽게 피해 갔잖아
Xu.
욱욱
Don't forget to write a report to my brother.
황형한테 상주서를 올려
I deserve the credit for this.
이 공로는 본왕의 것이니
Don't let Zhou Shiyu steal my thunder.
주시여가 득을 보면 안 돼
Yes.
예
But Your Highness, don't you find it weird?
하오나 이상하지 않습니까?
How did the North Prince know
남가에 자객이 있다는 걸
about the assassination in the South Street?
북왕이 어찌 알았을까요?
Yeah.
그러게
Did he send the assassins?
혹시 북왕이 사주한 건가?
It doesn't make sense.
아니지
If he sent the assassins,
본인이 사주한 거면
why did he tell me about it?
나한테 알려줄 리가 없잖아
Don't you think he has a problem
북왕과 동유 공주가
with the Princess of Dongyu?
이상하지 않아요?
It's so smart of you.
과연 똑똑해
They do have a problem.
정말 어딘가 문제가 있어
A problem with their relationship.
둘 사이가 갈라진 거야
But...
아니...
Chunhua, Qiuyue, Xiachan.
춘화, 추월, 하선
- Here.
예
You know best about women's hearts.
여자가 여자를 잘 아는 법이지
Teach me something.
공주의 마음을 얻는 법을
I'll keep pursuing the princess.
어서 알려주거라
- Count on us.
맡겨만 주십시오
- Let's go, Your Highness. - Come on.
왕야, 가시죠
But Your Highness...
아니, 왕야...
(It's so hard to work for you.)
(어찌 이런 멍청한 주인이 다 있어)
Your Highness, you've been carving the whole day.
왕야, 벌써 하루 종일 그러고 계셨잖아요
Have some refreshments.
어서 다과를 좀 드세요
Leave them there.
거기다 둬
Yes.
예
Prime Minister,
승상
I...
소인
I really don't understand.
소인은 정말 모르겠습니다
Why...?
어찌
Why can Zhou Shiyu
주시여가
know about all our plans in advance?
저희의 계획을 알아챈 건지 정말 모르옵니다
This time...
이번에
This time, I dispatched
소인이 보낸 사람은
my men of sacrifice.
다 제 수하들이니
There can't be an inside traitor.
내부인의 소행일 리 없습니다
Maybe we're guessing it wrong.
우리가 방향을 잘못 잡은 것 같다
What is
주시여한테
Zhou Shiyu's secret?
무슨 비밀이 있는 걸까
Greetings, Brother.
황형을 뵙습니다
Shiyu,
셋째야
I heard the other day,
며칠 전 너와 둘째
you, Chenyu, and the Princess of Dongyu
그리고 동유 공주까지
were assassinated.
자객의 습격을 받았다면서?
What? Were you hurt?
다친 데는 없느냐?
Everything is fine.
아무 일 없습니다
I'm having a secret investigation on it,
암암리에 조사 중이지만
but haven't found conclusive evidence yet.
아직 증좌를 확보하지 못했습니다
Glad you're fine.
무사하면 됐어
But Chenyu
하나 둘째는
was badly sick.
크게 아파서
I sent an imperial physician.
내가 어의까지 보내주었다
Don't be too serious
너희 둘이 하는 이 장난질
in the game with Chenyu.
적당히 좀 하려무나
He's slow-witted.
둘째는 미련해서
I fear he'll take it seriously.
진짜로 받아들일 수도 있어
You'd better concede to him.
네가 많이 봐줘
I will.
예
But I have one request.
한데 청이 하나 있습니다
Tell me about it.
말해 보거라
I want you to issue a decree.
황형께서 명을 하나 내려주셨으면 합니다
Your Majesty, it's done.
폐하, 분부하신 건 전부 준비하였습니다
Today,
셋째가
my youngest brother
동유 공주를 위해
requested a decree for the Princess of Dongyu.
명을 청하다니
Why?
이게 대체 웬일이냐
It has never happened before.
이런 상황은 처음이긴 하네요
Yeah.
그러게
Abnormal, indeed.
이상하다
Will you really not talk to me?
정말 나랑 말을 안 할 거야?
That's not true.
아니요
How may I serve you, Your Highness?
북왕 전하 무슨 분부가 있으신가요?
I'm used to your calling me Wen Yu.
그냥 문우라고 불러줘
Or call me Shiyu.
시여도 좋고
All right,
네
Your Highness.
북왕 전하
Still mad at me?
아직도 화 안 풀렸어?
I'm the fake Eldest Princess
동유에서 온
from Dongyu.
가짜 첫째 공주는
In Beishuo, I have no one to rely on.
북삭에서 의지할 곳 하나 없이
Without Your Highness's support,
오로지 북왕 전하 덕분에
I can barely live.
근근히 살아가고 있는데
How do I dare to be mad at you?
그런 제가 감히 전하께 화를 낸다니요
My brother gave you a Dongyu horse,
황형이 오늘 사냥을 위해
so we're going hunting.
동유의 말을 하사하였어
How about we stop arguing today?
오늘은 일단 휴전하자
Later,
이따가
you can enjoy a thrill ride.
말을 타며 실력을 한번 뽐내봐
All right.
네
The crossbow is for you.
이 쇠뇌를 받아
I'll teach you how to use it when hunting.
사냥할 때 어떻게 쓰는지 내가 가르쳐 줄게
You can also use it for self-protection.
호신용으로도 써도 되고
I think we should hunt separately.
따로 떨어져서 사냥하는 게 좋겠어요
I'm going out now.
난 밖에 앉아 있을게
(It seems to be made by hand.)
(직접 만든 것 같은데)
(He actually made it with care.)
(마음을 꽤 썼네)
Su Nian,
언니
I've invited that silly prince to come over.
그 멍청한 왕자와 약속을 잡았어요
Is everything ready out there?
밖에는 다 준비됐어?
Don't worry.
걱정하지 마세요
The instrument is put out there.
악기는 이미 밖에 놨고
Everything is ready.
다른 것도 다 준비됐어요
You're always gorgeous.
원래도 아름다우신데
When you use the lipstick that is recently popular in the Capital City,
거기다
you look even prettier.
더 아름다우시네요
Later,
이따가
you'll certainly fascinate that nerd.
저 멍청한 왕자가 홀딱 반할걸요
(The House of Romance)
(풍월각)
Miss Su Nian,
소염 낭자
where did you buy this lipstick?
그 연지는 어디서 산 것이오?
My wife asked me many times.
내 집사람이 몇 번이나 물어봤소
I always want to buy one for her.
집사람한테 사주고 싶구먼
It looks so pretty.
참말로 예쁘오
You...
당신
Xingyi?
성습 공자
Why did you punch me?
왜 나를 때리시오?
What is your problem?
제정신이오?
You tried to touch her.
여인한테 집적거리니까
I should punch you.
때리지
Such a lunatic.
미친놈 아니야
I won't bother to argue.
재수 없게
Leave quickly.
얼른 꺼져
Or I'll punch you again.
또 때리기 전에
Are you all right?
괜찮소?
Actually, he was just...
저자는 그저...
I know.
나도 안다오
I've seen a lot of guys like him.
저런 놈은 수도 없이 봤구려
If it happens again,
앞으로 이런 일 있으면
I'll help you.
내가 나서주리다
Thank you, then.
감사합니다, 공자
Oh, I'll teach you martial arts.
참, 무공을 가르쳐 주겠소
When you can do martial arts
무공을 할 줄 알면
and meet people like him again,
저런 놈을 만나도
you can rip them up.
직접 혼낼 수 있을 것 아니오
♪Wind♪
♪바람이 설레는 정담을 살포시 놓고 가요♪
♪Whispers of love♪
♪정담은 한 사람만 꺾을 수 있기에 아름답죠♪
A great horse, indeed.
과연 명마로군
A great horse from Dongyu.
역시 동유의 말은 달라
♪For the rest of my life♪
♪여생은 달빛을 보며 사랑을 속삭이고 싶어요♪
♪I'll remain elegant for you all my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 아름답고 싶어요♪
♪Giving you my love little by little♪
♪조금씩 사랑을 내려놓고♪
♪And I miss you every day and night♪
♪평생 그리워하죠♪
♪I'll be loyal to you in the best years of my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 노력할게요♪
♪Melting love with gentle smiles♪
♪웃음으로 사랑을 녹여요♪
♪I won't be afraid of anything♪
♪비바람이 불어도 두렵지 않아요♪
♪And I won't change my heart for you♪
♪해마다 거두는 찻잎처럼 말이죠♪
Yueling,
아월
you can try the crossbow.
쇠뇌를 한 번 써봐
You've nearly hunted all the rabbits.
덕분에 토끼가 달아났는데
Shall I try it against the tree?
뭘 쏘라고요?
Some more rabbits are there.
아니, 거기 또 있어
I'll ride over there.
난 저쪽에 갈 테니
Have a good time here alone, Your Highness.
북왕 전하는 혼자 여기서 즐기세요
Good.
좋소
We'll start with such simple moves.
간단한 것부터 연습합시다
To do martial arts, you must plant your feet steadily.
무공을 연마하려면 다리에 힘이 있어야 하오
It's really thought of you.
이리 세심하신 분인 줄 몰랐습니다
You cared this much for me.
저를 위해 신경을 많이 써주셨네요
This is what I should do. We're friends.
우리는 친구 아니오?
Don't be afraid of exhaustion.
혼자 힘들어하지 말고
I'll practice with you.
나도 같이 해주겠소
Thank you, then.
고마습니다
We're almost done, huh?
이 정도면 충분한 것 같소
I think
우리
we've been doing this for four hours.
두 시진은 한 것 같은데
But why do I feel
아니요, 반 시진밖에
we've only been doing this for one hour?
안 한 것 같은데요
How's that possible?
그럴 리가
I'm so tired...
힘들어 죽겠는데
No. I mean
아니, 내 말은
we've done enough today.
오늘은 이만하면 충분하오
How about
혹시
we take a rest for now?
좀 쉬지 않겠소?
It doesn't matter.
괜찮아요
I can practice for a bit longer.
더 버틸 수 있어요
I can't continue.
난 무리오
I really can't.
더는 안 되겠소
Are you all right?
괜찮으세요?
Let me get you there for a rest.
제가 저쪽까지 부축해드릴 테니
Come on.
일어나세요
No, thanks.
아니, 됐소
Let me help you.
부축해드릴게요
No need.
괜찮소
Su Nian, you're awesome.
소염, 정말 대단하구려
I'm too tired to continue.
나도 못 하겠는데
But you can keep doing it.
끝까지 버티다니
You have no idea.
공자는 모르죠?
We practice dancing
사실 무용은
just like how you practice martial arts.
무술을 배우는 것과 비슷해요
We focus on the center of body weight and strengths.
신체의 중심과 힘을 단련해야 하죠
That's why I can do this.
그래서 지금까지 버틸 수 있었어요
Now I finally know,
이제야 알겠구려
"One will not succeed
고생을 해야
before going through all the hardships."
성공할 수 있다고
You must have gone through a lot
낭자도 숱한 고생 끝에
before you became the most gorgeous lady her.
풍월각 제일가는 명기가 되었을 테지
Yueling!
아월
I'm here!
나 여기에 있어
how did you fall off the horse?
어쩌다 넘어진 거야?
My horse was startled.
말이 놀라서
I had to jump off it.
뛰어내렸어
Then I...
그래서...
Don't move.
움직이지 마
Yueling,
아월
how did you get hurt?
도대체 어떻게 다친 거야?
A branch fell...
아까 나무가 있었...
Any better?
괜찮아졌어?
You twisted your ankle.
발을 삔 거야
Let's take a rest somewhere.
일단 휴식할 곳을 찾고
When it stops snowing,
눈이 그치면
we'll ride away.
말을 타고 가자
All right.
그래
Come on.
자
- I want...
- 있잖아
You go first.
먼저 말해
We've come this far.
지금 우리 상황 말이야
Pretending to be my eldest sister,
난 그저 언니인 척
I came here.
이곳에 왔을 뿐인데
I didn't expect things to be so complicated.
일이 이리 복잡해질 줄 몰랐어
I don't know what to do now.
나도 생각이 정리가 안 돼
So, I think we should take care of the engagement
그러니 화친은
as soon as we can.
하루빨리 해결하자
That's exactly what I'm thinking.
나도 같은 생각이야
So, I want...
그래서 말인데...
Is there any way to break off this engagement?
혼인을 취소할 방법이 없을까?
What do you want to do?
넌 어떻게 하고 싶어?
I haven't made up my mind.
나도 잘 모르겠어
I just want to go home.
그냥 집에 가고 싶어
Give me three months.
석 달만 줘
I'll get you back to Dongyu by then.
꼭 동유에 돌아가게 해줄게
Really?
정말?
(I want you)
(난 네가)
(to stay by my side.)
(내 곁에 있어줬으면 해)
Clean carefully.
깨끗이 쓸어
Clear the way.
길을 터놔
Clean over here.
이쪽도
(Auspicious and Fortunate)
(재양응서)
Your Highness, you're up.
왕자님, 일어나셨어요?
Come get washed.
얼른 소세하세요
(The North Prince's Mansion)
(북왕부)
Greetings, Your Highness.
왕야를 뵙습니다
You twisted your ankle.
발 다쳤으니
Don't force yourself to walk.
무리하지 마
Her Grace is back.
왕비께서 돌아오셨어
Yueling, you're back.
누님, 돌아왔어요?
Your Grace, you're finally back.
공주님, 돌아오셨어요?
Have some rest.
일단 푹 쉬어
I'll have an imperial physician check on your sprain.
어의더러 상처를 봐주라고 할게
Sprain?
상처요?
- Yueling. - Your Grace.
누님
- Yueling, what happened? - Your Grace, what happened?
누님, 왜 그래요?
- Nothing. - You're injured?
다쳤어요?
Your sister twisted her ankle.
발을 다쳤어
Take good care of her.
잘 보살펴 줘
Twisted her ankle?
발이요?
How did that happen, Yueling?
누님, 어떻게 된 거예요?
Let me check.
좀 볼게요
I'm fine.
괜찮아
Your Grace.
공주님
Did he hurt you?
북왕이 한 거예요?
There he is.
오셨다
Your Highness.
왕야
You're awesome.
과연 왕야십니다
You either took no action
역시 행동으로 보여주는 것만큼
or took impressive action.
좋은 방법도 없죠
You made Her Grace happy so quickly.
순식간에 왕비님을 달래셨네요
You even stayed together
아름다운 곳에서
on such a beautiful night.
같이 하룻밤도 보내셨고요
Your Highness, you're so resourceful
과연 영명하십니다
and victorious...
백전백승이네요
Shut up.
시끄럽네
It hurts.
아파
I... I'll be gentle, then.
그럼 살살할게요
How about this?
이러면요?
How shall I put it?
어떻게 말해야 하지
I'll just ask.
모르겠다
Yueling,
누님
how could you stay out all night?
어젯밤에 왜 안 돌아왔어요?
I twisted my ankle. Can't you see?
나 발 삔 거 안 보여?
And it was snowing.
게다가 밖에 눈도 내렸어
You not only stayed out all night
밤새 안 들어온 건 그렇다 쳐도
but also spent the night with the North Prince.
상대는 북왕이고
He even carried you back.
심지어 북왕한테 안긴 채로 돌아왔잖아요
Yueling, you're pretending to be our eldest sister.
누님은 진짜 혼인 상대가 아니잖아요
We're going back to Dongyu someday.
결국 돌아갈 거 아니에요?
He promised me.
나한테 약속했어
In three months,
석 달 뒤에
we can go back to Dongyu.
동유로 보내주겠다고
Really?
정말요?
He lied to you so many times.
북왕이 거짓말을 몇 번이나 했는데
Can he still be reliable?
믿어도 되는 거예요?
Yueling, verbal statements are no guarantee.
누님, 말로만 하지 말고
I think you need a written guarantee.
보증서를 쓰라고 해요
You have a point.
네 말이 맞아
- Your Grace. - Yueling.
공주님
Where are you going?
어디에 가는 거예요?
Yueling, where are you going?
누님, 어디 가요?
- Your ankle hasn't recovered. - I'll go get a guarantee.
발이 아직...
Look. Clean over here.
이쪽도 쓸어
- Your Grace. - I'm fine.
왕비님
Come in.
들어와
Linmu, rub the ink stick for me.
임목, 먹을 좀 갈아줘
Yueling?
아월
You work really hard.
수고가 많네
So many things to handle.
처리해야 할 일이 많아서
Not really.
괜찮아, 안 많아
Why didn't you let me know you were here?
어찌 왔는데 말도 없어?
You didn't even look up.
고개도 안 들길래
So, I didn't disturb you.
가만히 있었지
Call me next time.
다음에는 그냥 날 불러
Is there some reason
무슨 일로
why you're here?
찾아온 거야?
Yes, I'm here for something.
일이 있긴 한데
But not a very big deal.
큰일은 아니야
Feel free to tell me.
말해 봐
You told me
지난번에 말한
I could leave in three months.
석 달 말이야
But you lied to me many times.
네가 한 거짓말이 한둘이 아니니
I'm afraid you may go back on your word.
이번에도 그럴까 봐 그러는데
May I ask for a guarantee or something?
계약서 같은 거 써주면 안 돼?
For example, a decree from your brother
황형께 혼인 날짜를 미뤄달라는
for the delay of the wedding.
황명을 받아오든가
All right.
그래
I'll get that for you.
그렇게 할게
You will?
정말?
(Benign and Benevolent)
(제월광풍)
♪Clouds slowly float across the sky♪
♪저 멀리 유유히 흐르는 구름♪
♪Telling what is awfully bothering♪
♪헤어지기 아쉽다 말하네♪
♪Ceaseless, love lingers and lingers♪
♪잘라낼 수 없는 그리움에 사로잡혀♪
♪You and I both know it♪
♪사랑하니까 말하지 않아도 알아♪
♪In this world, we stay side by side♪
♪속세에 비할 만큼♪
♪Watching the stars rise and fall♪
♪수많은 별똥별이 깜빡여♪
♪My eyes are red from missing you♪
♪붉어진 두 눈 그리움은 고치가 되고♪
♪Tonight, I hope the moonlight will♪
♪오늘 밤 밝은 달이 네 미간에 떨어지길 바라네♪
♪I'll always be in love with you♪
♪그대와 영원히 함께하고 싶다고♪
♪Promising it'll last forever♪
♪하늘에 맹세했더니♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪오동나무 꽃이 떨어지며 소원을 이뤄주고♪
♪To have joy for the rest of its life♪
♪남은 생은 웃음꽃만 피우리♪
♪I'll stay with you for thousands of years♪
♪그대와 만 년을 살고 싶어♪
♪Until we grow old together♪
♪백발에 하얀 눈이 내리는 꿈을 꿨네♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪산들바람이 오동나무 꽃을 스치며♪
♪When I look back, you whisper♪
♪그대를 나지막하게 불러♪
♪Then I wake up from the dream♪
♪꿈에서 깨어나 보니 여전히 첫 만남과 같네♪